<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A shorte treatise, of the crosse in baptisme contracted into this syllogisme. No humane ordinance becomming an idoll, may lawfully be vsed in the seruice of God. But the signe of the crosse being a humane ordinance is become an idoll: ergo· The signe of the crosse may not lawfully be vsed in the seruice of God.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856130</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 702:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A shorte treatise, of the crosse in baptisme contracted into this syllogisme. No humane ordinance becomming an idoll, may lawfully be vsed in the seruice of God. But the signe of the crosse being a humane ordinance is become an idoll: ergo· The signe of the crosse may not lawfully be vsed in the seruice of God.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.H. [i.e. William Jones' secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed in London by William Jones' secret press (STC).</note>
                  <note>D1 is cancelled; D2 is signed D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cross, Sign of the --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21653:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORTE TREATISE, OF the croſſe in Baptiſme con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tracted into this ſyllogiſme.</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>No humane ordinance becomming an Idoll, may lawfully be vſed in the ſeruice of God.</item>
               <item>But the ſigne of the croſſe being a humane ordinance is become an Idoll: </item>
               <item>ergo. The ſigne of the croſſe may not lawfully be vſed in the ſeruice of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Amſterdam <hi>Printed by</hi> I. H. <hi>1604.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="proof_texts">
            <pb facs="tcp:21653:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The latine avthorities Engliſhed.</head>
            <p n="1">1 They which will treat of all ſortes of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, muſt needes take the name of an Idoll in a larger ſignification. By the name therefore of an Idoll is vnderſtood: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beſides the true God a man doth pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe or frame to himſelfe to be worſhipped, either ſimplie, or in ſome reſpect.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For Idolls or images haue greater power to corrupt a ſilly ſoule, in that they haue a mouth, eyes, eares, noſe, handes, feete, then to correct it, in that they neyther heare, ſmell &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſigne of the Croſſe which is made in the forehead, or in the ayre, is ſacred and venerable.</p>
            <p n="4">4 We adore the ſigne of the Croſſe, by which we haue receaued the Sacrament of ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The chriſtians from Chriſts time hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervnto haue worſhipped with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt loue, both the woode of the Lords croſſe, &amp; the ſigne of the croſſe: with which they
<pb facs="tcp:21653:2"/> dayly fence themfelues.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Defend me Ieſu, from all euill vices paſt, preſent: and to come, by the ſigne of holy croſſe: and by the in eſtimable price of thy iuſt and precious bloud.</p>
            <p n="7">7 If thou ſeeke any law for this in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thou ſhalt find none. Tradition is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouched to be the author, cuſtome the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmer, and faith the obſeruer.</p>
            <p n="8">8 At euery paſſage, at euery ſetting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, at euery cominge in and goeing out, at putting on of our clothes, ſhoes, &amp;c. We stampe our forhead with the ſigne of the croſſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9 And with often croſſinge guard thy for head, that the deſtroyer of Egipt find no place in thee.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Chriſts followers doe by the ſigne of the Croſſe, ſhut out the vncleane ſpirites.</p>
            <p n="11">11 The Croſſe guardeth the minde, it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth revenge on the deuill, it cureth the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeaſes of the ſoule &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whoſe vertue, perfecteth all ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes:
<pb facs="tcp:21653:3"/> without which ſigne nothing is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor any conſecration tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th effect, and whoſoeuer are the Miniſters of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whatſoeuer hands doe dypp or annoynt the comers to Baptiſme, out of whatſoeuer mouth the ſacreed word doe proceed, the authoritie of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration doth by the ſigne of the Croſſe, make effectuallall Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>craments.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21653:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>OF THE SIGNE OF THE</hi> Croſſe in Baptiſme. The vſe of the Croſſe in Baptiſme is not a thing indifferent, but vtterly vnlawfull. For this reaſon.</head>
            <p>IT is againſt the Apoſtles precept 1. Io. 5.21.<note place="margin">PROOFES OF THE MAIOR.</note> 
               <hi>Babes keepe your ſelves from Idolls.</hi> For the explanation wherof two thinges are to be ſcanned firſt: what is meant by an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll. Secondly: how farr we are to keepe our ſelues from the Idoll. An Idoll is<note place="margin">whatſo euer beſides God is worſhiped with divine honor.</note> 
               <hi>quicquid preter deum diuino colitur honore:</hi> and though ſome reſtraine an Idoll to a viſible forme: becauſe it is deriued of <hi>apotou eidous</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et as a learned writer obſerueth<note place="margin">Zanch. de re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dem P. lib. 1. cap, 17, Thſ. 5:</note> 
               <hi>Qui de omnibus Idolatrie generibus acturi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt, latius nomen Idoli accipiant ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt Idoli igitur nomine intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur quicquid homo tanquam deum vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpliciter vel <hi rend="sup">katati</hi> ſibi extra verum Deum proponit fingitque colendum.</hi> Neither is this ſpoken without good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, for nothing is properly an Idoll,<note place="margin">as it is a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble forme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but as it is religiouſly worſhiped.</note> 
               <hi>quate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s eſt viſibilis forma, ſed quatenus reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſe colitur</hi> If therefore it be worſhipped it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21653:4"/> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be an Idoll though it be no viſible ſhape otherwiſe the worſhipping of Angells and the ſoules of the iuſt men were no Idolatry, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe are inviſible ſpirites. and therefore the ſigne of the Croſſe. If it be religiouſly worſhipped, may proue an Idoll though it be <hi>tranſiens quiddam</hi> a thinge vaniſhing in the Ayre and no permanent forme. For as that learned Zanche ſpeaketh there is a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex<note place="margin">A twofould Idol the on reall the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>narie con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued only in the minde</note> Idolum, the one reall the other <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narium et tantum mente conceptum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer to the Second queſtion. Men may keepe themſelues from Idolls two wayes viZ. <hi>a cultu, et ab vſu Idoli</hi> from the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipp, and from the vſe of the Idoll. For the firſt,<note place="margin">How farr we are to keepe our ſelues from an Idoll, 1 Cor. 10.15, to 23.</note> S. Paule is ſo ſtrict that he alloweth not the chriſtians ſo much as to be preſent in the temple at the Idolatrous feaſts, though they did it without any internall opinion, or externall action of worſhippinge the Idoll.</p>
            <p>But Iohn in this place doth not ſpeake ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much of the worſhip as the vſe of the Idoll for (as Aug. in pſalme 113. well obſerueth) th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21653:4"/> Apoſtle commaundeth <hi>vt caueant non tan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum a cultu ſimulacrorum, ſed a ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacris ipſis.</hi> that they a voyd not only the worſhipp of the Images, but alſo the images or Idolls themſelues.</p>
            <p>Now the vſe of an Image, or Idoll, may be ciuill or religious, and both of them publike or priuate.</p>
            <p>That an Image, even ſuch an Image as is Idolatrouſly worſhipped, may be made &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for cyvill reſpects of ornament, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or ſuch like: we make no queſtion. though the tollarating of them in open and publick places, even <hi>extra cultum</hi> be offenſiue and turne into a ſnare, as Gideons Ephod was to his poſteritie: when it was abuſed to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. And vppon this ground we yeld, that though the Croſſe be apparantly an Idoll, yet in Princes Banners, Coronations, Coyne, Crowne, or any other cyuill reſpect it may haue a lawfull vſe. But that any thinge of mans deuiſinge being worſhipped as an Idoll ſhould be uſed <hi>religionis ergo</hi> &amp; in the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipp
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21653:5"/> of God, ſeemeth directly againſt S. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> precept, for, how doe I keepe my ſelfe from the Idoll, or how doe I ſheew my Zealous d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtation of that filthy Idolatry: when I r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne it: and vſe it ſo honorably, as in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Temple, in the Sanctuary, in the ſervice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God. Which interpritation of this place of S. Iohn, the Church of England<note n="e" place="margin">Homil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ga, perill of Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie part 2</note> doth on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> warrant of Tertullian approue &amp; comend.</p>
            <p>And this poynt is further ſtrengthened by the ſecond commaundement:<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 23 &amp; 34 13 Deut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7.5, Pſ, 16, 4</note> which forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not only to worſhipp: but even to make any Image, or any ſimilitude whatſoeuer, to witt, <hi>ad cultum,</hi> or for religious vſe: as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſcripture the beſt<note n="g" place="margin">Caluin, inſti. li : 1 cap. 11 V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. cathe. in expoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cundi, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. Petr. Martyr loc com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claſ 2 cap 5; sect 22 Hooper in 2 precePt. Zanch: de re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib 1 c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> interpret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ors, partly againſt Images in Churches, part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly on the words of the precept doe moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally expound it. for ſuerly, if Idolatry it ſelfe as amoſt execrable thing be forbidden, then all occaſions and meanes leading there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto are likewiſe prohibited. And what ſtronger prouocation to that ſpirituall whor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome: then erectinge Images in the place of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21653:5"/> Gods worſhipp? <hi>Plus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Babington on the 2. commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. Perk. ſet: cauſ. ca, 21 Allen on the 2 Com. Dod on the 2. com,</note> 
               <hi>enim vt rectu Av<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinus in</hi> pſal. 113. <hi>Valent ſimulacra ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uruandam infelicem animam, quod os <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abent, oculos habent, aures habent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares habent, manus habent, pedes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, quam ad corrigendam quod non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oquentur, non videbunt, non audient, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on odorabunt, non tractabunt, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbulabunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore without doubt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of the commaundement is to bynde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Church: from all ſuch ſnares and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uerments to ſinne, and therefore doth Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtyne in queſt. ſuꝓ Leuit. q. 68. well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onclude from this commaundement that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch making of an Idoll can neuer be iuſt or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awfull.</p>
            <p>Now if no ſimilitude at all be tollarable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Gods ſervice, then much leſſe any that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath bene and is worſhipped Idolatrouſly.</p>
            <p>Tertullian againſt the Gnoſtickes: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompted them Idolaters not only which wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hipped, but thoſe alſo which made and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21653:6"/> Images (nemppe ad cultum or for ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vſe) and in his booke de Idolatria, he ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hemently reproued the very makers of Ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, though they did not themſelues wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipp them, which ſheeweth in what execra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion the primitiue Churches held any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vſe of an Idoll.</p>
            <p>The like we may finde in Epiphanius ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iohannem Epu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m Hicroſal. Where he repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that finding an image of Chriſt, or ſome Saint, hanging at a Church dore, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent it in peeces, avouching that to hang a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> picture in the Church of Chriſt, was <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra autoritatem ſcripturarum contra re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem chriſtianam:</hi> contrary to the authoritie of the ſcriptures and the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion.</p>
            <p>From hence I conclude, that if the godly fathers were ſo vehement againſt erecting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Images of Chriſt, and of Saintes, even a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that time: before any worſhipp was giuen vnto them. Much more would they with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand it now after men haue made Idolles of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21653:6"/> them. And if they would not ſuffer an Idoll ſo much as in the place of Gods worſhip: would they endure themſelues to vſe ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>doll as the Croſſe: in the ſeruice and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God. Their Zeale againſt that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fornication: would neuer permitt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem ſo highly to honor, ſuch an execrable thing: neither was their Zeale herein with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ground of knowledge: For the ſpirit of God in Pſa. 115.8. ſpeaking of Idolls, They (ſaith he) that make them, are like vnto them, and ſo are all they that truſt in them. Where a plaine difference is made: betweene makers: and worſhippers of Idolls: and both condemned, as curſſed tranſgreſſors of the law, ſhall any then make the Idoll of the croſſe and that <hi>religionis cauſa</hi> and yet be innocent?</p>
            <p>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtionleſſe by Dauids<note place="margin">Pſa 16, 14</note> example we muſt make no mention, that is keepe no hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable memory of an Idoll, and therfore with out doubt: not giue it ſo much honor as to vſe it: or the memoriall thereof in the houſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21653:7"/> of God, and in his holy worſhipp, but as Iſai ſaith<note place="margin">Isai 50.22</note>, We muſt pollute the reliques: and the very couering, and ornament of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll, &amp; caſt them away as amenſtrous cloth, and ſay vnto it gett thee hence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">PROOFE OF THE MINOR</note>Now if any doubt whither the ſigne of the croſſe be adored: and ſo made an Idoll, lett him well conſider the tract of Bellarmine <hi>de a doratione crucis,</hi> where diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Croſſe on which Chriſt was hanged, from the ſimilitude thereof he ſaith,<note place="margin">other croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes like to this, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Images</note> 
               <hi>cetere cruces illi ſimiles inter ſacras imagines numerantur</hi> and after he diſtinguiſheth thoſe ſimilytudes of Chriſtes Croſſe into the Image and ſigne of the Croſſe, ſo that if the Image of the croſſe be taken for an Idoll (&amp; who knoweth not that it is the vniuerſall I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll of popery: and to be adored, euen <hi>cultu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie</hi> (which worſhipp as they themſelues hould is due only vnto God) the ſigne of the croſſe muſt needes be taken for no better. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſame,<note place="margin">De Image lib, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Bellarmyne hauing as is ſaid diſtinguiſhed the croſſe: into three ſortes: the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21653:7"/> croſſe, the Image of the croſſe, and the ſigne of the croſſe, he layeth downe this doctrine generally of them all, <hi>omnes cruces ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi> and perticulerly of the ſigne of the croſſe he ſaith,<note place="margin">we adore all croſſes de Imag. lib, 2 cap. 29.</note> 
               <hi>ſignum crucis quod in fronte vel in aere pingitur eſſe ſacrum et venerabile.</hi> To this agreeth Portiformus Sariſb: 4 where it is thus profeſſed <hi>adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus crucis ſignaculum per quod ſalutis ſumpſimus ſacramentum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the Image and ſigne of the croſſe is of one, and the ſame account with papiſts, appereth evidently as by diuers: ſo perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by Hart: For Docter Raynoldes<note place="margin">Confer: with Hart Cap; 8: diuiſ-4</note> ſheewing that the Church of England, hath iuſtly left the ſigne of the croſſe out of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per for the Idolatry thereof, doth proue that it is worſhipped as an Idoll, by ſuch teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies as indeede belonge to the Image of the croſſe, which Hart no way excepted againſt, doth imply, that looke what eſtimation they haue of the Image: the ſame they haue of the ſigne, and what honor is due to the one: is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21653:8"/> due to the other. For in very deed, they care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully teach,<note place="margin">Andra. or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod: e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pli lib 9. Bellarm. de imag, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b, 2 cap, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 Tho. Aquin part 3. q. 2 art. q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art. &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uers other</note> that it is not in regard of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> matter, wherein the croſſe is painted, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> couler whereby it is ſhaddowed, but only an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſimply for the expreſſing of the liknes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtes croſſe, and for the repreſenting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt crucyfied (which the ſigne perform<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth as well as the Image) that the adore th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> croſſe with the ſame honor, that is due vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt himſelfe. And this no doubt was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meanning of <hi>Aquinas</hi> when he ſaith th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>every effigies</hi> or liknes of the croſſe (wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of the ſigne is one) is to be adored <hi>cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrie</hi> and Coſterus doth avouch that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame worſhipp is due to the ſigne,<note place="margin">Ibidem</note> as belong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth to the very croſſe of Chriſt, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaith (though falſly)<note place="margin">Coſter. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, cap 11,</note> 
               <hi>chriſtiani a Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> temporibus ſemper ſumma venerati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne coluerunt ipſum ſignum dominic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crvcis et ſignum crvcis qvo ſe qvotidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maniunt</hi> Marke that the ſigne of the cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is worſhipped <hi>ſumma veneratione</hi> with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> higheſt degee of honor, and as<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thod. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce. lib, 9:</note> Andra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21653:8"/> in expreſſe words ſaith in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, that the Image of Chriſt himſelfe is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſhipped, then the which what can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore clere to proue that not only the Image: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the ſigne of the croſſe is by the papiſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt Idolatrouſly worſhipped?</p>
            <p>Yf any ſay that to the ſigne of the croſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one boweth the knee or vaileth the bonnet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd therfore it is not adored. I anſwer. Firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat adoration is interne and externe: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he externe adoration is therfore Idolatry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe it proceedeth from the interne, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ancheus<note place="margin">Zanch: de re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempt. lib 1 ca: 17 Theſ: 5</note> very learnedly, and largely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeweth.</p>
            <p>Yf a man invocate to an Angell or giue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y honor internall to a creature, ſhall it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e called Idolatry,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.6 Coloſ. 3 5</note> exceept he bowe outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto it? How then doth Paull ſay that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etouſnes is Idolatry? For a rich man doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot outwardly worſhipp his goodes, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſe he giueth vnto it interne<note place="margin">Mark 10 24 1 Tim 6 19 Luke 12: 15</note> confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich is due vnto God, it is truely called his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>doll, as vnto the Sardanapali<note place="margin">Phii 3.19</note> there belly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21653:9"/> is termed there god: Right ſo the Papiſtes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribinge to the ſigne of the croſſe, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and confidence which belongeth to God, doe make it an execrable Idoll: and ſo moſt vnfitt to ſtand in the ſanctuary, or to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the holy thinges of God. For firſt they aſcrybe vnto the ſigne of the croſſe: power and vertue, to mcryt pardon at leaſt for veniall ſinnes,<note place="margin">queſt, dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, de venal pecto</note> as appea-reth by (r) Tho. Aquinus (s) Bellermine and (t) Rhemiſtes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">de effect sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crument. li 2 1 Tim 4 ſect 13.14 Bellar. de ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect sacr. lib 2. cap, 31 Vnto a rude clowne whos dull vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge cannot reach to hig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>her thinges, this only (ſaith h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) ſufficeth for his ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>Alſo it is held to partake of power effici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent, and imediatly (v) operatiue, and that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conuert ſinners Marſhal de cruce fol. 114 115. yea to gaine ſaluation, Hoſius (x) contra Brent. p. 227. and generally the whole rabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Romiſh Doctors do teach to putt great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance in this ſigne for chaſing away deuils, and curinge diſeaſes, and ſanctifiynge both man, and other creatures, to the vſe of man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay indeed they doe giue out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, aſwell as inward worſhipp to the croſſe. For it is apparant that they invocate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21653:9"/> it in the ſame manner, that they invocate ſaints whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſay <hi>per crucis hoc ſignum fugiat procul omne malignum</hi> by this ſigne of holy Croſſe let euills all flie farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Againe, by the ſigne of the holy Croſſe,<note place="margin">In officio ſanct. cruce printed in Engliſh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1599.</note> from our enimies dcliuer vs o Lord our God Alſo in another place, victorious Croſſe and admirable ſigne, make vs triumph and ioy: in heauenly courtes divine. Yea in prayers they ioyne it with Ieſus Chriſt, as in <hi>officio miſſae</hi> is to be ſeene, where they ſupplicate:<note place="margin">By the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Ieſus Chriſt, by the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de &amp; ſigne of the croſſe, by the interceſſion of the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed virgine,</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>per miſe ecordiam Ieſu Chriſti, per aux ilium et ſignum crucis, per interceſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem beate Mariae</hi> &amp;c. They couple it alſo with the bloud of Chriſt in theſe words defend me Ieſu <hi>ab omnibus vitiis, malis preteritis, preſentibus et futuris, per ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſanctae crucis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">hor. preſent ad uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Pariſijs impre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1498.</note> 
               <hi>et per ineſtimabile pretium iuſti et pretioſi ſanguinis tui.</hi> All which doth moſt manifeſtly proue, that amonge the Papiſtes it is religiouſly honored <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth with inward confidence, and outwarde reuerence. And therfore if their Idolls may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21653:10"/> in no ſorte be annexed to the ſeruice of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, the croſſe in Baptiſme ought neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be croſſed &amp; curſed out of our liturgy Neither is it a ſufficient anſwer to ſay, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the croſſe amongſt vs is <hi>neque numero n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>que vſu,</hi> the ſame that theirs is, and thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their croſſe be an Idoll, yet ours is not. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when God commaunded his people to break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe the Images of the heathen and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the very name of them, had they performed that charge if they had burnt al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Idolls of Canaan, and afterwarde mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> newe of the ſame forme, and to another vſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though not Idolatrous: yet religious? or how haue we diſcharged our dueties and ſheewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our deteſtation of that filthy Idolatry, if ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing defaced all the popiſh crucifixes and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls, we erect them newe in our Church though not to worſhipp them, yet to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy vſe whatſoeuer. It is true that our croſſe and theirs is the ſame, both in name, and forme, but not in vſe, for then were it I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dolatrous, now I doe not ſay that the church of England, doth commit Idolatry: but that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21653:10"/> it ought to abſteine not only from the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or worſhipp, but euen from all religious vſe of ſuch humaine ordinances and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which others haue and doe Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly adore. For, if to erect crucyfixes, and other popiſh Images for holy vſe be (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the commaundement) a keeping of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable memory of the Idoll,<note place="margin">Exod: 23.15 Deut: 12:3. Hos. 2.17.</note> howe can the religious vſe of the croſſe in Baptiſme being aſwell an Idoll as any of their Images be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned without breach of the law, <hi>Babes keepe your ſelues from Idolles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>obiection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſigne of the croſſe in the firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was free from ſuperſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and if the abuſe which grewe after be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mooued why ſhould it not recouer his aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vſe &amp; indiffrency, like as as the bread in the Lords ſupper which the Papiſtes doe religiouſly adore?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are Churches, Pulpets &amp;c. thinges of neceſſarie vſe and war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ranted by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. but the reteyning of the brazen ſerpent was noe where commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is great difference betweene that which God hath created and commaunded
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21653:11"/> and that which man hath ordeyned, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one is neceſſary and no abuſe can alter t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nature of it, the other indifferent and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buſe may become vnlawfull; and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Hezekia did worthely breake the braſen ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent not ſeekinge to redreſſe the abuſe of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Now howſoeuer Bellarmyne would inſinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the croſſe is founded on ſcripture, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the weaknes of his argumentes doe bewray the vnſoundnes of the matter,<note place="margin">aut enim ſg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>num crucis habere vim ſperitualem Potiſſimum ex inſtituto Dei li. 2. de effect: ſacra. et li. 2. de Imag ca: 29 conatur ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationem, crucis scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture autori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tate ſtabilire de corona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mi!.</note> and therfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tertullians iudgment is to be preferre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which plainly ſaith, that there is no warran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ſcripture for it <hi>horum inquit</hi> (7) <hi>ſi le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gem poſtules ſcripturarum nullam in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies, traditio tibi pretenditur autrix co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuetudo confirmatrix fides obſervatrix</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe it is further to be noted that a dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble vſe of the Croſſe is mentioned in antiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, one ciuill, the other religious, againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> former we doe not diſpute yeldinge all reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence, to thoſe chriſtians which by that not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſheewed their reioycinge and glory, in that which the heathen counted their ſhame, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21653:11"/> now, that abuſe hath turned both the Image and the ſigne of the Croſſe into an Idoll, it ſeemeth thereby to be made execrable. For Gideons Ephod beinge firſt a ciull monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of victory, when the people went a whoring after it, was it lawfull for the Magiſtrate to erect in the tabernacle or ſinagogue though not the ſame, yet the like, both in name and forme to any religious vſe? would it haue ſufficed to ſay this is not the ſame Ephod that Iſraell maketh an Idoll of neither is it ſett heere to be worſhipped (for your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe grevouſly ſinne therin) but only to keepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n minde they great victory that God by Gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deon gaue to Iſraell? Right ſo the croſſe vſed by the auncients to ſheew that they were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhamed of Chriſt crucified being meerely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yuill, and yet expreſſinge a moſt chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſolution, hauing bene abuſed, yea, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to be worſhipped, both in <hi>imagine</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>ſigno,</hi> it ſee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth that this filth hath made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t vnfitt, on any pretence of reſtoringe it to his auncient vſe to be annexed to the holy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21653:12"/> thinges of the ſanctuarie: eſpecially wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their are ſo many papiſts that ſuperſtition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe it among vs. Now for the religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vſe of the croſſe by the auncientes, it was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer free from ſinne and ſuperſtition as afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes is ſheewed, and if it were, yet it bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an humaine ordinance, and now not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buſed to Idolàtrie, but becominge it ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt abominable Idoll, no water can clen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it, nor any pretext purifie it for the holy ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vice of Iehouah. But in very deed to ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the truth is, the croſſe is reteined among vs with opinion very ſuperſtitious and er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nious, for in the late Canons it is ſaid, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the child<note place="margin">Canon 30.</note> is therby dedicated vnto the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice of him that died on the croſſe. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this but to equall mans ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and to aſcribe that vnto the croſſe, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> due vnto Baptiſme? a conceite fitter for ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>narant papiſtes, then learned chriſtians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſſent vnto. Neither doe we vſe it as the au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cientes did, for Cyprian, Auguſtine, Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtome &amp; others,<note place="margin">Turtul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de bapti; ca. 7.8 Euseb. li 6, ca. 48, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent 1, epiſt, cap. 3. Rab. ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de inſti. cleric. cap, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Durand. de ritib. eccles. li. 1. cap. 20,</note> it is apparant that thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21653:12"/> times did conſecrate the elimentes therwith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd did not croſſe the childs forhead at all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut referred that vnto the Biſhopps confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, ſo that our croſſing the Infants for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead and not the element of Baptiſme, is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eere noueltie without any warrant of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntyquitie,<note place="margin">Our vſe of the croſſe a Noveltie of ſome 60-yeares ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> neither will that place of Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ian <hi>de reſurrectione carnis</hi> proue the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rary. The fleſh is waſhed that the ſoule may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e purged, the fleſh is annoynted, that the ſoule may be conſecrated, the fleſh is ſigned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the ſoule may be guarded, the fleſh is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hadowed by the impoſition of handes, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſoule may be by the ſpirit inlightened, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he fleſh doth feed on the bodie and bloud of Chriſt, that the ſoule may be filled and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of God. In which wordes he ioyninge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eather diuers cerimonies of the chriſtians, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth indeede mention the ſigninge of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aithfull, but it may as well be referred to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſed by impoſition of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to Baptiſme, vnderſtood by the waſhinge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the body, and that one better reaſon, for it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21653:13"/> is more than probable that the ſigne of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> croſſe was not yet vſed in Baptiſme, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> in defenſ. <hi>ad Antonin</hi> a &amp; <hi>Tertull. de Baptiſmo et de corona mil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial his epiſt are iuſtly ſuspected:</note> doe deſcribe the forme of Baptiſme vſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in thoſe times and yet make no mention o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the croſſe therin, which in all liklyhood the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would not haue omitted if it had bene vſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therin eſpecially Tertullian, who in that ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry place ſpeaketh of the croſſe, as vſed out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſme in the ordinarie bleſſing of them ſelues.</p>
            <p>obiection.</p>
            <p>But the ſigne of the croſſe is not vſed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſme, but when baptiſme is ended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yf you take Baptiſme only for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dipping &amp; ſprincling of the partie it is tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſo none of the popiſh additions, whereby they defile that holy ſacrament are in bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, for thoſe which <hi>Apud Bellar. Baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> comitantur</hi> are not impious, but if you tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> baptiſme as indeed we doe: for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of that ſacrament, then both th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayers before and the prayers after, the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21653:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> after the dipping: doe all indifferently belong to one and the ſelfe ſame thinge, yea it is all <hi>vna et)</hi>
               <note place="margin">on continual action of the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament.</note> 
               <hi>continua actio admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrationis ſacramenti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure it is that it muſt be ſaid to be, either in <hi>baptiſmo extra baptiſmum aut nullibi,</hi> if it be out of baptiſme,<note place="margin">In Baptiſme or out of Bapr. or no where,</note> how is it by common conſent of all, ſaid to be <hi>ſignum crucis in baptiſmo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obiect. The ſigne of the croſſe is very aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
            <p>Anſ. So are many other popiſh traditions. And if on that ground we are to retaine it, why doe we not giue the baptiſed<note place="margin">milke &amp; ho</note> 
               <hi>lactis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et mellis concordiam.</hi> Why doe we not bring offrings for the dead. For Turtullian the firſt of the Fathers that euer mentioned the Croſſe: doth eſtabliſh theſe, and the ſigne of the croſſe by one and the ſelfe ſame war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantie. Beſides, if vpon the fathers traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we vſe the croſſe, then muſt we receaue and vſe it as they haue deliuered it vnto vs that is, with opinion of vertue and efficacie,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21653:14"/> not only in the act of bleſſing our ſelues, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the expelling of diuills, but even in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſecration of the bleſſed Sacramente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For the firſt, Tertullian is w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes<note place="margin">de coron mil</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>omnem progreſſum, ad omnem promotum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad omnem ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad veſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> et calce atum, frontem crucis ſignaculo ferimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> For chaſinge of deuills, Ierom councelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Demetrius to vſe the croſſe.<note place="margin">Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtol. 1 ad Demetriam.</note> Et crebro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9 <hi>inquit ſignaculo crucis munias frontem tua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne extermmator Aegipti in te locum reperia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lactantias (de hoc ſigno ſcribens)<note place="margin">lib. 4 cap. 17</note> ait clirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſactatores, inquinatos ſpiritus, ſigno paſſioni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> excludere Chriſoſtom: in pſal. 108. (11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crux inquit munit mentem: ea Demones v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cilcitur ea tollit morbos anime.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe ſuperſtitions are ſmall in regard of that efficacie which in the ſacraments, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiquitie aſcribed vnto the croſſe, for Cypr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an (being the auncienteſt that maketh me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the croſſe in Baptiſme) ſpeaking of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(12) cuius vertus omnia peragit ſacramenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſine quo ſigno nihil eſt ſanctum, neque aliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſecratio meretur effectum. &amp; againe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian de pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> 
               <hi>Qui cunque ſunt ſacramento ruin miniſtri, quale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21653:14"/> cunque ſunt manus que vel mergunt acceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es ad baptiſmum vel vngunt qualecumque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectus de quo ſacra exeunt verba, operationis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utoritas in figura crucis omnibus ſacramentis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgitur effectum, Auguſtine in Ioh: tract. 18. Quod ſignum inquit niſi adhibeatur ſiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontibus credentium ſiue ipſe aque qua regene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antur fiue oleo quo chriſmate inunguntur ſiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crificio quo aluntur nihil eorum rite perficitur</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were ſuperfluous to reherſe the reſt. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereby it is evident that the religious vſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he croſſe, was even at the firſt ſinnfull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uperſtitious, neither can it be ſheewed,<note place="margin">without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtvre of ſupertition:</note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer it was vſed by the Fathers, religionis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>go ſine admixta ſuperſtitione, and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did noe ſooner creepe into the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent but it drewe vnto it ſelfe ſuch ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous conceite of efficacie and neceſsitie, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithout it, the meanes which God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for the conſecration of the elements ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed over weake, yea, vnauailable according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſome<note place="margin">Latly in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey a child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rebaptiſed becauſe the croſſe was omitted,</note> amongſt vs account not theire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hildren lawfully baptiſed, yea, will haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem rebaptiſed, if the croſſe haue bene omit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, out of which may be obſerued, firſt how
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21653:15"/> dangerous a thing it is to bring in any h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane inuention into the ſeruice of God, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the very pure age of the Church, it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> puniſhed with ſuch a ſpirituall curſe of ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, though at this time popery w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not hatched, yet the miſterie of iniquity w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then a working, and the begining as it wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the whoriſh fornications was found eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Fathers times, ſo that, as worſhippin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Angells in Paules time,<note place="margin">Coloſ: 2.18:</note> prayers &amp; oblati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons for the dead in Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s time, be righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly counted popiſh and Antichriſtian, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as yet that monſter was not borne. So this &amp; other Ceremonies ratified by the popiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nons &amp; conſtitutions, may well be taken for popiſh &amp; Antichriſtian, euen in the Father times, ſeeinge they then made away for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beaſt, and ſince haue receaued further impl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etie and autoritie from him:<note place="margin">Esai. 52, 11,</note> wherfore to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude as Iſai exhorteth Gods people, to keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelues from the rites and pollutions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the heathen, ſaying, depart depart ye, goe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21653:15"/> from them &amp; touch noe vncleane thinge. So the ſpirit in the ſame manner chargeth the Church not to medle with the corruptions of Antichriſtian Babilon,<note place="margin">Apoc, 18, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but goe out of her my peoplc ſaith he, that ye may not be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues.</p>
            <p>The feare of which curſe doth keepe us from all the ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous cerimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of that whoriſh ſinagogue.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>pag. 10. ſignum, for lignum, pag 11. inuocate to, for inuocate, <hi>15</hi> inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of, for inuentions.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
